<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM 'BioC.dtd'><collection><source>PubTator</source><date></date><key>BioC.key</key><document><id>10090891</id><passage><infon key="journal">Am. J. Hum. Genet.; 1999 Apr; 64(4) 1063-70</infon><infon key="year">1999</infon><infon key="article-id_pmc">PMC1377830</infon><infon key="type">title</infon><infon key="authors">Lee HS, Sambuughin N, Cervenakova L, Chapman J, Pocchiari M, Litvak S, Qi HY, Budka H, del Ser T, Furukawa H, Brown P, Gajdusek DC, Long JC, Korczyn AD, Goldfarb LG</infon><offset>0</offset><text>Ancestral origins and worldwide distribution of the PRNP 200K mutation causing familial Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease.</text></passage><passage><infon key="type">abstract</infon><offset>115</offset><text>Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease (CJD) belongs to a group of prion diseases that may be infectious, sporadic, or hereditary. The 200K point mutation in the PRNP gene is the most frequent cause of hereditary CJD, accounting for &gt;70% of families with CJD worldwide. Prevalence of the 200K variant of familial CJD is especially high in Slovakia, Chile, and Italy, and among populations of Libyan and Tunisian Jews. To study ancestral origins of the 200K mutation-associated chromosomes, we selected microsatellite markers flanking the PRNP gene on chromosome 20p12-pter and an intragenic single-nucleotide polymorphism at the PRNP codon 129. Haplotypes were constructed for 62 CJD families originating from 11 world populations. The results show that Libyan, Tunisian, Italian, Chilean, and Spanish families share a major haplotype, suggesting that the 200K mutation may have originated from a single mutational event, perhaps in Spain, and spread to all these populations with Sephardic migrants expelled from Spain in the Middle Ages. Slovakian families and a family of Polish origin show another unique haplotype. The haplotypes in families from Germany, Sicily, Austria, and Japan are different from the Mediterranean or eastern European haplotypes. On the basis of this study, we conclude that founder effect and independent mutational events are responsible for the current geographic distribution of hereditary CJD associated with the 200K mutation.</text><annotation id="7"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="142" length="3"/><text>CJD</text></annotation><annotation id="8"><infon key="identifier">36469</infon><infon key="type">Species</infon><location offset="169" length="5"/><text>prion</text></annotation><annotation id="9"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="315" length="3"/><text>CJD</text></annotation><annotation id="10"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="357" length="3"/><text>CJD</text></annotation><annotation id="11"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="415" length="3"/><text>CJD</text></annotation><annotation id="12"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="782" length="3"/><text>CJD</text></annotation><annotation id="13"><infon key="Identifier">MESH:D007562</infon><infon key="type">Disease</infon><location offset="1512" length="14"/><text>hereditary CJD</text></annotation></passage></document></collection>